INVENTORY TO THE PIERCE FAMILY PAPERS, 1841-1940 D-022
University of California, Davis General Library, Dept. of Special Collections
- George W. Pierce, Jr., 1864-1931; Series 3.; 1328 Linear Feet
  - Diaries, Notes, and Meeting Minutes, 1866-1930; Subseries 3.4.; 136 items
    - Diary, 1907; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Diary and accounts, 1908; 1 volume (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Diary and accounts, 1909; 1 volume; 1 clipping (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Diary and accounts, 1910; 1 volume (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes (informal summary), Silica Brick Company, 1910-1912; 3 leaves. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Diary and accounts, 1911; 1 volume; 2 leaves. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Diary, 1912; 1 volume (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Diary and accounts, 1913; 1 volume; 1 clipping (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Diary and accounts, 1914; 1 volume (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Diary and accounts, 1915; 1 volume (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Diary and accounts, 1916; 1 volume (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Diary and accounts, 1917; 1 volume (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Diary and accounts, 1918; 1 volume; 1 leaf (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Notes on farm labor, circa 1918; 3 leaves.; 1 envelope (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Diary and accounts, 1919; 1 volume (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Diary and accounts, 1921; 1 volume (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Diary, 1922; 1 volume (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Diary, 1923; 1 volume (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Diary and Notes on travel in Mediterranean and Middle East, 1924; 1 volume (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Diary and Notes on travel in London and Windsor, 1924; 1 booklet (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Diary, 1924; 1 volume (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Diary, 1925; 1 volume (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Diary, 1927; 1 volume (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Diary and accounts, 1928; 1 volume (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Diary, 1928-1929; 1 volume (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Diary, "My Cruise Round the World on Canadian Pacific, S.S. Empress of Australia", 1928-1929; 7 items 1 volume, pencil, 2 cards, sticker, ink blotter, and map (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Notes on Imperialism and the Philippines, Feb. 12, 1929; 1 envelope; 13 leaves. (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Diary entries and notes on Canadian Pacific shore excursions into China, Hong Kong, Japan, Java, and Singapore, Feb. 13-March 5, 1929; 3 Volumes annotated travel guides; 13 leaves.; 1 envelope (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Diary and accounts, 1929; 1 volume (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Diary, 1930; 1 volume; 2 clippings (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Notes and sketches, various, undated; 10 leaves. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Creative Works, [1860]-1925; Subseries 3.5.; 113 items
    Creative Works make up the 5th subseries of Series III, George W. Pierce, Jr. These creative works are further divided into three categories: Inventions, Literary Productions, and Other. Inventions include records of an almond bleacher patented in 1923 by Pierce and information gathered in a Baker and Hamilton ledger (1917-1925), which was created by an unidentified person who likely was from Yolo County, CA. The ledger contains photographs, diagrams, and notes about farm machinery and would be of great interest to historians of agricultural technology. Pierce's Literary Productions are articles written about Davis, CA; Yolo County, CA; almonds; and the selection of the University Farm site. The article, "Selection of University Farm Site," is found here in two forms: a typed draft and a photocopy of a handwritten draft. The original handwritten draft was made on the reverse side of a draft of a letter from Pierce to Governor George C. Pardee and is housed among Pierce's outgoing correspondence to Pardee. Other literary productions in this subseries are a poem, a satire presented to the Davisville Whist Club, a speech given on the occasion of the first commencement at the Davis Joint Union High School, an empty envelope that once held an "Almond Address," and the outline for a speech or article promoting Davisville, CA as the best site for the proposed University Farm. Other materials in the Creative Works subseries are labels for a Yolo County, CA exhibit, a handwritten program for a school play, and a scrapbook. The Scrapbook, which may have been created by George W. Pierce, Jr., is a circa 1860s account book with clippings pasted over most of its pages. The clippings are of poems, recipes, works of fiction, comments on liquor and drunkenness, and other articles of general interest. Many loose clippings, notes, fliers, and newspapers were also inserted between the pages of this scrapbook and have been removed either to a folder of 85 loose clippings that accompanies the scrapbook or to other locations within the Pierce Family Papers (as noted on a separation sheet).
    - Inventions, 1917-1925; Subseries 3.5.1.; 3 items
      - Almond Bleacher, by George W. Pierce, Jr., n.d., U.S. patent and time line, 1923; 2 items (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Diagrams and 7 photographs of farm machinery in Baker and Hamilton ledger, 1 volume, 1917-1925; 1 item (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Literary Productions, 1904-1928; Subseries 3.5.2.; 14 items
      - Articles, n.d., ca., 1905-1913; 5 items (Box 6, Folder 15)
        "The Almond," "As We Appear to Outside Eyes," "Davis," and "Selection of University Farm Site"
      - Poem, n.d., 1 item (Box 6, Folder 16.1)
      - Satire, "The War in the Far East," to the Davisville Whist Club, 3 leaves, March 5, 1904; 3 items (Box 6, Folder 16.2)
      - Speeches, ca., 1905-1928; 5 items
        - On the occasion of the first commencement at Davis Joint Union High School, text of speech on 3 leaves, 1928; 3 items (Box 6, Folder 17.1)
        - Envelope (empty) that held, "Almond Address," made to the Davis Fruit Growers' Convention, June 1914; 1 item (Box 6, Folder 17.2)
        - Outline of a speech promoting Davisville, CA as the site for the University Farm, ca., 1905; 1 item (Box 6, Folder 17.3)
    - Other, n.d., 1864-1889; Subseries 3.5.3.; 96 items
      - Scrapbook, 1865-1889; 86 items
        - Account book converted into scrapbook, 1 volume, 1865-1889; 1 item (Box 6, Folder 18)
        - Loose clippings from scrapbook, 1865-1889; 85 items (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Exhibit Labels, Yolo County, CA, n.d., 9 items (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - Program (handwritten) for school play, March 5, 1864; 1 item (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Printed Material, n.d., 1867-1930; Subseries 3.6.; 433 items
    The sixth subseries, Printed Material, is the largest of Series III, George W. Pierce, Jr. It contains 433 items (1867-1930) and is divided into the subseries subjects: Business Ventures, California Promotion, Farmers's Marketing Organizations, Highways, Labor, the Panama-Pacific International Exposition, Travel, the University of California, and Other. Items under these subject headings may be further divided by subject and then are finally arranged by the format of the materials such as clippings, newsletters, newspapers, lists, broadsides, fliers, brochures, bulletins, books, and pamphlets.
    - Business Ventures, 1882-1914; Subseries 3.6.1.; 17 items
      Under Pierce's Business Ventures, the researcher will find brochures and a list of lot prices for the Diggs Subdivision of the Hext Tract in Davis, CA, an 1882 broadside for the Putah Creek Water Company, a statement for Sacramento Clay Products Company, 2 lists of Sacramento Valley Electric Railroad Company stockholders along with newspapers describing that company's activities, and estimates of construction costs and a statement for the Silica Brick Company. The 3 newspapers containing information about the Sacramento Valley Electric Railroad Company are the "Sacramento Union" (Jan. 19, 1914) and the "Woodland Daily Democrat" (Jan. 19, 1914 and Dec. 8, 1914). These newspapers feature such headlines as: "Donahue Ousted, G. W. Pierce Now in Power, Willows Man Deposed as Head of Sacramento Valley Electric and Yolo Man Elected," "George W. Pierce, Head of Railroad: Election held by Sacramento Valley Electric in San Francisco Saturday," and "Yolo Man in a Suit Filed against R. R."
      - Diggs Subdivision of the Hext Tract, Yolo County, CA; 2 brochures and a list of lot prices; n.d., Feb. 1, 1907; 3 items (Box 6, Folder 22)
      - Putah Creek Water Company; broadside;., 1882; 1 item (Box 10, Folder 9)
      - Sacramento Clay Products Company; statement, 1912; 1 item (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - Sacramento Valley Electric Railroad Company, n.d., 1914; 5 items
        - List of stockholders in Sacramento Valley Electric Railroad Company, n.d., 2 items (Box 6, Folder 24)
        - Newspapers with articles relating to Sacramento Valley Electric Railroad Company,., 1914; 3 items (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - Silica Brick Company, estimates of plant and equipment costs and a statement, 1910-1912; 7 items (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - California Promotion, n.d., 1889-1926; Subseries 3.6.2.; 25 items
      Printed material, collected by George W. Pierce, Jr. and related to California promotion, is divided into material promoting individual California counties (Contra Costa, Fresno, Sacramento, San Diego, and Yolo) or the State in general. The material is then further divided by format such as newsletters, menus, brochures, lists, bulletins, clippings, newspapers, pamphlets, fliers, and a postcard. Pierce contributed articles promoting the virtues of Yolo County, CA to many publications including the pamphlets: March 26, 1915, Yolo County Exposition Number (commemorative of Yolo County Day at the Panama-Pacific International Exposition) of the "Woodland Democrat" and the Democrat's August 23, 1926, "Yolo County in Word and Picture." A circa 1889 fragment of a newspaper, "Pacific Coast Commercial Record," features a group of articles about prominent Yolo County, CA figures and businesses. Fliers for a Picture Tour of California seem related to a 1903 postcard (housed in Pierce's incoming correspondence) to Pierce from F. W. Crandall discussing the promotion of this traveling slide show.
      - Counties, n.d., 1889-1926; 14 items
        - Contra Costa County, CA; Newsletter, "The Richmond Times,", Dec. 1922; 1 item (Box 6, Folder 26)
        - Fresno County, CA; Menu, Dec. 14, 1907; 1 item (Box 6, Folder 27)
        - Sacramento County, CA, n.d., May [1916]; 4 items
          - Brochures, n.d., 3 items (Box 6, Folder 28.1)
          - List of prizes for Causeway Celebration Floral Parade, May [1916]; 1 item (Box 6, Folder 28.2)
        - San Diego County, CA; Bulletin., 1 item (Box 6, Folder 29)
          Cristadoro, C., ed., "Dry Farming Possibilities and Small Farms," San Diego, CA: San Diego Board of Supervisors and Chamber of Commerce, 1915
        - Yolo County, CA; n.d., 1889-1926; 7 items
          - Clippings, n.d., 1913-1918; 3 items (Box 6, Folder 30)
          - List of exhibitors and products, Yolo County, CA, exhibit, n.d., 1 item (Box 10, Folder 11)
          - Newspaper fragment., 1 item (Box 10, Folder 12)
            "Pacific Coast Commercial Record," San Francisco, CA: ca. 1889, pp. 3-6.
          - Pamphlets,., 1915-1926; 2 items (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - California State, n.d., 1902-1922; 11 items
        Printed Material, collected by George W. Pierce, Jr. and having to do with the promotion of the State of California in general, is contained in the California State subseries (1902-1922). The 11 items in this subseries are bulletins, a clipping, fliers, a pamphlet, and a postcard with attached ribbons and button. The two bulletins are: "Monthly Bulletin of the California Development Association, Agriculture and Industry, for January 1922," San Francisco, CA: Feb. 4, 1922 and "Monthly Bulletin of the California Development Board," San Francisco, CA: July 1912.
        - Bulletins, 1912-1922; 2 items (Box 6, Folder 31)
        - Clipping, ca., 1918; 1 item (Box 6, Folder 32.1)
        - Fliers, Picture Tour of California, 1903; 3 items (Box 6, Folder 32.2)
        - Pamphlet; "Speech of United States Senator A. J. Beveridge, of Indiana," San Francisco, CA:, 1902; 1 item (Box 6, Folder 33)
        - Postcard with attached ribbons and button, n.d., 4 items (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Farmers' Marketing Organizations, n.d., 1902-1928; Subseries 3.6.3.; 112 items
      Printed material having to do with Farmers' Marketing Organizations includes many items relating to the California Almond Growers' Exchange, a few items pertaining to other farmers' marketing organizations, and general information about how farmers marketed their crops. The items are arranged first under the name of the organization with which they have to do and then by their format such as books, brochures, bulletins, certificates, clippings, envelopes, fliers, labels, lists, menus, newsletters, pamphlets, postcards, reports, and store displays.
      - California Almond Growers' Exchange, Davisville Almond Growers' Association, and Davis Almond Growers' Association, 1903-1923; 78 items
        - Book; "California Almonds," San Francisco, CA: California Almond Growers' Exchange, 1918; 1 item (Box 12, Folder 4)
        - Brochures; n.d.,; 4 brochures, 2 handwritten notes, and 1 clipping, 1910-1920; 7 items (Box 6, Folder 35)
        - Brochures, oversize,., 1919-1920; 2 items (Box 10, Folder 13)
        - Bulletin, San Francisco, CA: California Almond Growers' Exchange, Oct. 14, 1919; 1 item (Box 6, Folder 36)
        - Certificate, Davis Almond Growers' Association,., May 4, 1910; 1 item (Box 10, Folder 14)
        - Clippings,., 1919; 6 items (Box 10, Folder 15)
        - Envelopes, n.d., 3 items (Box 6, Folder 37)
        - Fliers, n.d., 9 items (Box 6, Folder 38.1)
        - Fliers, oversize, n.d., 2 items (Box 10, Folder 16)
        - Labels, n.d., 8 items (Box 6, Folder 38.2)
        - Lists (membership, products, prices), n.d., 1903-1920; 8 items (Box 6, Folder 39)
        - Pamphlets, n.d.,., April 9, 1920; 9 items (Box 6, Folder 40)
          "By-laws of the Almond Growers Association," and "By-laws of the California Almond Growers Exchange."
        - Pamphlet., 1 item (Box 6, Folder 41)
          "Shall the American Almond Industry Perish?" San Francisco, CA: California Almond Growers' Exchange, ca. 1921.
        - Postcards, n.d., 1919; 2 items (Box 6, Folder 42)
        - Reports, 1922-1923; 2 items (Box 6, Folder 43)
        - Store displays, banners and broadsides, n.d., 10 items (Box 10, Folder 17)
        - Store displays, booklet with posters for advertising campaign,., 1919; 1 item (Box 11, Folder 1)
        - Store displays, cardboard cut-outs, n.d., 5 items (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - California Bean Growers' Association
        - Clipping, 1918; 1 item (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - California Fruit Growers, 1908-1917; 3 items
        - Clipping,., Jan. 17, 1908; 1 item (Box 11, Folder 3)
        - Menus, Nov. 23, 1917; 2 items (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - California Grain Growers
        - Certificates and lists of canvassers and subscribers, n.d., 7 items (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - California Prune and Apricot Growers
        - Brochure, 1918; 1 item (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - California Walnut Growers' Association, 1919-1920; 3 items
        - Book; "The California Walnut," Los Angeles, CA: California Walnut Growers' Association, 1919; 1 item (Box 12, Folder 6)
        - Brochure with store displays,., 1919; 1 item (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - Newsletter; "Diamond Brand News," vol. II, no. 2, March 1920; 1 item (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - The Farmers National Cooperative Exchange Company
        - Brochure and clipping, 1902; 2 items (Box 7, Folder 3.1)
      - The Farmers' Protective Association of California
        - Circulars, n.d., 2 items (Box 7, Folder 3.2)
      - The National Grange
        - Clipping, 1928; 1 item (Box 7, Folder 3.3)
      - The National Society of Equity of North America
        - Clipping, n.d., 1 item (Box 7, Folder 3.4)
      - General, n.d., 1918-1922; 10 items
        - Clippings, n.d., 2 items (Box 7, Folder 4)
        - Clipping, oversize, Feb. 5, 1918; 1 item (Box 11, Folder 5.1)
        - Fliers, "How the Tariff Affects the Farmer," n.d., 3 items (Box 11, Folder 5.2)
        - Newsletters., 2 items (Box 12, Folder 8)
          "The Express Messenger," Nov. 1919and "Pacific Farm Progress," Feb. 1922
        - Pamphlet, n.d., 1 item (Box 7, Folder 5)
          Weinstock, H., State Market Director, "The Burden for Better Marketing Rests with the Farmer and Not with the State."
        - Food Products Supplement to the issue of "The Literary Digest Grocery Store.", Nov. 15, 1919; 1 item (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Highways, 1903-1915; Subseries 3.6.4.; 9 items
      The Highways subseries consists of printed materials, collected by George W. Pierce, Jr., that have to do with highways and roads. The materials include a political broadside which features images of early Yolo County, CA roads, clippings, a newspaper, and a pamphlet.
      - Broadside; "Good Roads or Political Roads, Which? M. P. Ormsby, Republican nominee for Supervisor, Second District,", Nov. 6, 1906; 1 item (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Clippings, 1913; 6 items (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Newspaper; "Woodland Daily Democrat,"., April 9, 1915; 1 item (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Pamphlet; Brownlow, W. P., "Why Wagon Roads in the United States are Bad and How They can be Improved," ca.., 1903; 1 item (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Labor, n.d., 1888-1918; Subseries 3.6.5.; 41 items
      George W. Pierce, Jr. was keenly interested in labor issues especially since he employed many laborers on his ranch. He collected items written about labor issues and attended meetings dealing with farm labor and the upheaval of laborers in general. The Labor subseries of Pierce's printed materials contains some of the labor-related materials that he collected. The bulk of the items found in this subseries are newspaper clippings (1917-1918). Other items consist of a flier, a form, meeting minutes, a newsletter, and a pamphlet. Also included is an envelope that may have been used by Pierce to store clippings or other labor-related information.
      - Clippings, n.d., 1917-1918; 32 items (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Clippings, oversize, 1918; 2 items (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Envelope, n.d., 1 item (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Flier featuring article; McConnell, G. W., "The Hard Times of Prosperity," ca.., 1917; 1 item (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - Form, Sutter Growers' Association, n.d., 1 item (Box 7, Folder 11.1)
      - Minutes of a joint meeting of committees on food production and labor conservation, Commonwealth Club, San Francisco, CA,; minutes and envelope, May 15, 1918; 2 items (Box 7, Folder 11.2)
      - Newsletter; "The Anglo and London Paris National Bank," San Francisco, CA:., Jan. 1, 1918; 1 item (Box 7, Folder 12)
      - Pamphlet; "The President's Message, Hostile to Home Protection, Home Markets, and Home Labor: Remarks of Hon. Justin S. Morrill, of Vermont, in the Senate of the United States,"., April 11, 1888; 1 item (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Panama-Pacific International Exposition, San Francisco, CA, 1914-1915; Subseries 3.6.6.; 24 items
      The printed Panama-Pacific International Exposition materials in this subseries were collected by George W. Pierce, Jr. during his frequent visits to the Exposition in San Francisco, CA in 1915. 11 brochures that Pierce picked up at the Exposition will be of interest to researchers of Agricultural Technology. These 1915 brochures advertise products made by the Chattanooga Plow Company, International Harvester Company, Newell Sanders Plow Company, and the Siphon Ventilator Company. A book, a brochure, a magazine, and a catalog describe the wonders of the Exposition itself, while 8 brochures allude to Southern California's 1915 Exposition. The Panama-Pacific International Exposition subseries is divided into materials about agricultural technology, the Exposition (information about it), and Southern California. These subject categories are further arranged by format of materials.
      - Agricultural Technology, brochures (collected at the Panama-Pacific International Exposition), 1915; 11 items (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - The Exposition (information about it), 1914-1915; 5 items
        - Book and envelope; "The Panama-Pacific International Exposition, Illustrated in Color," San Francisco, CA: Reid, Robert A.,., 1915; 2 items (Box 7, Folder 15)
        - Brochure, 1914; 1 item (Box 7, Folder 16)
        - Catalog; "Temporary Catalogue of the Department of Fine Arts: Panama-Pacific International Exposition," San Francisco, CA: Wahlgreen Company,., 1915; 1 item (Box 7, Folder 17)
        - Magazine; "Pacific Service Magazine," San Francisco, CA: Pacific Gas and Electric Company,., March 1915; 1 item (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - Southern California; brochures (collected at the Panama-Pacific International Exposition) relating to Los Angeles, CA and the Panama-California Exposition in San Diego, CA., 8 items (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Travel, n.d., 1867-1930; Subseries 3.6.7.; 121 items
      An avid traveler, George W. Pierce, Jr. collected a large amount of printed travel materials. Most of these materials have to do with the world cruises that he began to take near the end of his life. Travel materials here are listed by the country that they describe and then by the format of the material. The formats include brochures, cards, envelopes, pamphlets, programs, books, maps, schedules, tickets and passes, a broadside, lists, menus, a newsletter, and newspapers. The newspapers, two copies of the Nov. 17, 1924, "Woodland Daily Democrat," feature the headlines: "Germany Leads Europe, Says Geo. W. Pierce; American Scenery Superior to Europe, Yolo Man Declares; George Pierce Discovers Business Dull Everywhere but in Germany." Researchers interested in guide books and travel brochures as well as cruises during the 1920s would do well to examine these printed travel materials. Also, the printed travel materials complement Pierce's travel diaries and tour notes which are included in the Diaries, Notes, and Meeting Minutes subseries.
      - Algeria, 1928; 3 items
        - Brochure, card, and envelope, 1928; 3 items (Box 7, Folder 20)
      - Egypt, 1928-1929; 3 items
        - Pamphlet; Quibell, A. A., "The Pyramids of Giza," ca.., 1928; 1 item (Box 7, Folder 21)
        - Programs, 1928-1929; 2 items (Box 7, Folder 22)
      - England, 1924; 6 items
        - Book: "Cambridge," Reigate: Frith, F. and Company, ca.., 1924; 1 vol. (Box 7, Folder 23)
        - Book: "Guide book to Windsor Castle and the town and neighborhood of Windsor," Windsor: Oxley and Son,., 1924; 1 vol. (Box 7, Folder 24)
        - Book: Lawrence, G. C., ed., "The British Empire Exhibition, 1924, Official Guide," London: Fleetway Press,., 2 items (Box 7, Folder 25)
          book and two maps
        - Pamphlet, Ely Cathedral, ca., 1924; 1 item (Box 7, Folder 26)
      - France, 1922-1924; 5 items
        These printed materials are books (travel guides) describing destinations in Paris, France.
        - "Cook's Guide to Paris," London: Cook, Thomas and Son,., 1924; 2 items (Box 7, Folder 27)
          Book and map
        - "Paris in eight days and a day in Versailles," London: Librairie Hatchette,., 1922; 2 items (Box 7, Folder 28)
        - "Paris, Musee de l'Armee, Hotel des Invalides," Paris: Societe des Amis du Musee de l'Armee, ca.., 1924; 2 items (Box 7, Folder 29)
      - Gibraltar, ca. 1928; 6 items
        - Brochures and program in an envelope; ca., 1928; 6 items (Box 7, Folder 30)
      - Italy, 1924-1925; 3 items
        These printed travel materials are 2 guidebooks for Rome, Italy.
        - Scaglia, P. S., "The Catacombs of Rome, the Monuments of Italy-N. 14," Rome: Frank, Joseph, ca.., 1924; 1 item (Box 7, Folder 31)
        - Tani, A. D., "New Guide to Rome and its Environs," Rome: Verdesi, Enrico,., 1925; 2 items (Box 7, Folder 32)
          book and map
      - Japan, ca. 1929; 11 items